Guide to the Baher Azmy Papers, 1986-2007 and undated RL.00061
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Baher Azmy papers
1986-2007 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Azmy, Baher
RL.00061
1.8 Linear Feet
Professor of law at Seton Hall University and attorney representing Guantánamo detainee Murat Kurnaz. The Baher Azmy Papers span the years 1986-2007 and document Azmy's efforts for the writ of habeas corpus and the release and repatriation of his client Murat Kurnaz, a citizen of Turkey and permanent resident of Germany who was held in extra-judicial detention by the U.S. military at Guantánamo Bay Naval Base, Cuba. The material documents Baher Azmy's legal motions and public efforts for writ of habeas corpus and the release and repatriation of his client, Mr. Kurnaz. Legal papers are composed of filings and petitions; correspondence comprises letters from and to Baher Azmy, Murat Kurnaz, his family and friends, diplomatic officials and U.S. government offices; writings include Azmy's personal notes pertaining to the case and notes of his interviews with Murat Kurnaz; press clippings consist of media coverage regarding the Murat Kurnaz case in the U.S. and German press. Also includes electronic files of legal documents, notes, media releases, and correspondence. Materials are chiefly in English, but there are German and Arabic items, some of which are translated.
1,125 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Baher Azmy Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2009.
Collection Overview
The Baher Azmy Papers span the years 1986-2007, and consist of legal papers, correspondence, writings and press clippings. Materials pertain to the 2001 arrest in Pakistan of Turkish citizen and legal resident of Germany Murat Kurnaz, and his subsequent detention at the U.S. military base in Kandahar, Afghanistan and eventually at Guantánamo Bay Naval Base, Cuba. His detention was related to the Bush administration's responses to the September 11, 2001 air attacks in the U.S. He was released in 2006 and became the first former Guantánamo detainee to testify before Congress in 2008 about his experiences of detention, including military abuse and interrogation. The papers consist almost exclusively of written documents with the exception of a few printed images, and electronic files of legal documents, notes, media releases, and correspondence. The material documents Baher Azmy's legal motions and public efforts for writ of habeas corpus and the release and repatriation of his client, Mr. Kurnaz. Legal papers are composed of filings and petitions; correspondence comprises letters from and to Baher Azmy, Murat Kurnaz, his family and friends, diplomatic officials and U.S. government offices; writings include Azmy's personal notes pertaining to the case and notes of his interviews with Murat Kurnaz; press clippings consist of media coverage regarding the Murat Kurnaz case in the U.S. and German press. There are also several files concerning the religious group Jama¯at Tapli¯k (sometimes referred to as Jama'at al-Tabligh or Tablighi Jamaat). While the Baher Azmy papers contain material chiefly in English, the collection also holds German language materials, some of which are not translated into English. There is only one document written in Arabic to which an English translation is attached. Collection folders are arranged in alphabetical order by title within each box.
Biographical Note
Baher Azmy is an Egyptian-American lawyer and Professor of Law at Seton Hall University Law School Center for Social Justice, specializing in constitutional law. Azmy gained his law degree from the University of Pennsylvania. Aside from his academic pursuits, he takes pro bono publico cases. He took on the high-profile case of Guantánamo detainee Murat Kurnaz in July 2004. He is one of the first attorneys who were allowed to visit the Camp Delta military detention facility in Guantánamo Bay, Cuba. Azmy discussed legal concerns and human rights issues regarding the status of and practices in Guantánamo in various national and international academic and human rights platforms, also testifying before Congress. Some of his publications include Epilogue to Murat Kurnaz Five Years of My Life (Palgrave) 2008, Rasul v. Bush and the Intra-Territorial Constitution, 62 N. Y. U. Ann. Surv. Am. L. 369 (2007), Symposium Foreword: Guantánamo: How Should We Respond, 37 Seton Hall. L. Rev. 685 (2007).
Related Material
Dorsey & Whitney Records, 1997-2008, bulk 2004-2008, and undated [U.S. law firm also representing Guantánamo detainees]
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Tapli¯k Jama¯at; War on Terrorism, 2001-2009 -- Prisoners and prisons, American; Prisoners of war -- Government policy -- United States; Prisoners of war -- Abuse of -- Cuba -- Guantánamo Bay Naval Base; Military interrogation -- Government policy -- United States; Prisoners of war -- Cuba -- Guantánamo Bay Naval Base; Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp; Habeas corpus -- United States; Detention of persons -- Cuba -- Guantánamo Bay Naval Base; Azmy, Baher; Azmy, Baher; Kurnaz, Murat, 1982-
- Baher Azmy Papers, 1986-2007 and undated, 3 boxes
  - Administrative Review Board (ARB) proceedings (Box 1)
  - Attorney-client private motion (Box 1)
  - Azmy correspondence to Murat and government and news clippings (Box 1)
  - Azmy v. Department of Defense (DoD) Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) - challenged documents (Box 1)
  - Complaint, FOIA/Kurnaz (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and documents from Murat Kurnaz and Rami Ben Saad Al Utaybi (Box 1)
  - Detention of Murat Kurnaz and other case files of Guantánamo detainees I-II, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) request (Box 1)
  - Kurnaz client note 2005 July 23 (Box 1)
  - Kurnaz correspondence 2006 Feb. 2 (Box 1)
  - Kurnaz declassified documents - interview notes, letters (Box 1)
  - Kurnaz - Filings (M. Kurnaz and R. Kurnaz v. Bush, Rumsfeld, Hood, Cannon) (Box 1)
  - Kurnaz interview notes (Box 1)
  - Kurnaz motion for preliminary injunction (PI) and exhibits (Box 1)
  - Petition for habeas corpus and Azmy's notes on meetings with German and Turkish diplomats (Box 1)
  - Administrative Review Board (ARB) materials and submissions (Box 2)
  - Appointment of counsel motion and order (Box 2)
  - Counsel access procedures (Box 2)
  - Court orders (J. Green) (Box 2)
  - Declassification request (Box 2)
  - Defendant's motion for summary judgment (Box 2)
  - German affidavits and interrogation, translated (Box 2)
  - Government's consolidated opposition and exhibits (Box 2)
  - Government's response re: Murat (Box 2)
  - Habeas submission, key documents (Box 2)
  - Kurnaz transition memos (Box 2)
  - Materials sent to Turkey (Box 2)
  - Other Turkish detainees (Box 2)
  - Photos from Germany trip, 2005 Spring (Box 2)
  - Re: Defendant's motion for summary judgment (Box 2)
  - Second declaration of David M. Hardy (Box 2)
  - Azmy's research notes on Jama¯at Tapli¯k (religious apolitical group) (Box 3)
  - Azmy's research on Jama¯at Tapli¯k (Box 3)
  - Defendant's motion for summary judgment I-II, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Electronic Records, 2004-2008 (Box 3)
    Scope and Contents note
    Electronic files of legal documents, correspondence, research notes, publicity and media documents, memos from U.S. and German officials, and other material pertaining to Azmy's defense of Murat Kurnaz.
    Conditions Governing Access note
    [Files are located on the library server. For access to these materials, please consult with a reference archivist.]
  - Experts on Jama¯at Tapli¯k (Box 3)
  - Review of Combatant Status Review Board re: Kurnaz I-IV, 4 folders (Box 3)